Huh?
（太郎(たろう)）
えっ？　降りるって
Find someone else? You mean for that cut?
あのカットを
やらないってことですか？
No, for episode 8! The whole thing!
（遠藤(えんどう)）
違う　８話の作監をだ
Takanashi Tarou
Production Assistant
Endou Ryousuke
Animation Director
Slow down there! You can't really be quitting!
待ってくださいよ！
作監降りるって
マジじゃないっすよね？
Is this just an industry-standard negotiation tactic?
業界によくある
駆け引きの１つですよね？
I'm not bluffing! I mean it!
駆け引きじゃねえよ！
本気だ！
Endou-san!
遠藤さ～ん！
Miyamori Aoi
Production Assistant
How can you stand there and watch? Go stop him!
見てたんなら なんで
遠藤さんを止めてくんないんだ！
あっ あの
昨日の電話って…
Is this why you called me yesterday?
Yeah! Why weren't you taking me seriously?
そうだよ！
なんで もっと真剣に俺の話
聞いてくんなかったんだよ！
You didn't say a word about this!
そんな話
してなかったじゃないですか！
This is your fault!
お前のせいだ！
My fault?!
私のせいですか？
Well, maybe half your fault.
いや 半分くらいは きみの…
Half?
半分？
Okay, a third.
３割くらいはあなたの…
Seriously?
３割？
Or rather, one tenth, ma'am.
じゃあ １割くらいお嬢さまの…
It's not even a tenth. And don't "ma'am" me.
１割もないです！
お嬢さまでもないです！
I'm sorry! Just help me, please!
すいません
相談に乗ってください！
Yano Erika
Production Assistant
What's going on?
（矢野(やの)）
何やってんの？
O-Oh, nothing much.
（太郎）
えっ あっ 別に
なんでもありませ～ん
The morning meeting's about to start.
（あおい）えっ？
（矢野）朝礼始まるよ
Right...
（太郎）
すいませ～ん
Um, Takanashi-san, about this...
あの高梨(たかなし)さん 今の件ですけど
What? You have an idea?
何？　妙案浮かんだ？
That's not it! Shouldn't you tell Honda-san about this?
そうじゃなくて
本田(ほんだ)さんに報告したほうが
いいんじゃないですか？
No goddamn way!
いや！　いやいやいや…
I'm out of ideas.
Honda Yutaka
Production Manager
（本田）
万策尽きました～
The last episode's storyboards still aren't finished,
最終話のコンテが
まだ上がりません
and they were supposed to be done by September 20th.
本来のアップ予定が９月20日
So they're a month late now.
現時点で１か月ちょっと
遅れてます
Do you have an ETA?
（渡辺(わたなべ)）
上がる見込みは？
Nope. I don't have the slightest clue.
（本田）
見通しは まったく立ってません
How much is ready to go?
（丸川(まるかわ)）
今 どれくらいなの？
He's only done six of the twenty-four script pages.
（本田）
シナリオ 24ページ中
６ページくらいまでです
（あおい･太郎）ああ…
（矢野）４分の１ですか
Only a quarter done?
Kinoshita-kun can be quite difficult.
Marukawa Masato
President
木下(きのした)君も なかなかあれだね～
He started work on the storyboards on August 1st.
コンテインが８月１日
At this rate we won't be done until the end of January!
今のペースだと
来年の１月いっぱいかかります
Watanabe Jun
Line Producer
ああ…
オンエア終わっちゃってるね
That's past the air date.
I'm completely out of options! What am I supposed to do?
完全にお手上げです
もうどうしていいか
Okitsu Yuka
General Affairs
Honda-kun. Is it time to use the secret weapon?
（興津(おきつ)）
本田君 例のもの使う？
うん 俺は鬼になる！
I will become the devil.
If You're Gonna Blame Others
for Everything, Just Quit!
Fried chicken!
Kinoshita Seiichi
Director
（木下）
から揚げ～
Fried chicken! Fried chicken!
から揚げ から揚げ♪
How nice of you to buy some just for me!
悪いね～
わざわざ買ってきてくれたの？
But why is it in there?
あっ でも なんでこの部屋？
Storage
Oh right, it'd be bad if the director's booth smelled like food all day.
ああ 演出ブースに匂いが
こもっちゃうもんね
Storage
Whatever!
まあいいや
から揚げ から揚げっと…
Storage
Fried chicken! Fried chicken!
Whoa, it's dark in here.
あれっ 暗いよ
（ドアが閉まる音）
（本田）奥へ進んでください
Keep moving, please.
Could you get the lights first?
（木下）電気つけないの？
（本田）壊れてまして
They're out.
（木下）ふ～ん… あっ 痛っ！
（ぶつかる音）
（木下）痛っ～！
（本田）頭 下げてください
Duck down, please.
You tricked me!
俺をハメたな？
You're not leaving until you finish the last episode's storyboards.
（木下）
最終話の絵コンテが上がるまで
ここから出しません
You're keeping me prisoner?!
“出しません”って
What about the background
and coloring meetings? The art checks?
背景打ちや色打ちや
ボードチェックはどうすんの？
The filming meeting? The rush checks?!
撮影打ちに
ラッシュチェックは？
You'll be attending cutting and dubbing.
（本田）
カッティングとダビングには
出てもらいます
And the voice recording?
（木下）アフレコは？
（本田）フンッ！
No!
（木下）
イヤだ～！
No! No! No!
やだ やだ やだ…
Throwing a tantrum won't help.
だだこねてもムダです
閉じ込められたって
上がんないもんは上がんないよ～！
I can't work under these conditions! I won't!
やだ やだ… ハッ！
Oh right! I'll call—
そうだ！　誰かに… あっ
My phone!
俺の携帯！
I'll keep this until you're done.
（本田）
終わるまで預かっておきます
Seriously?
マジ？
Get to work.
（本田）描いてください！
（木下）あっ…
Get to work.
描いてください！
Honda-kun, you're scaring me.
本田君 怖いなあ
Um...
（木下）あのさあ
（本田）なんですか？
What is it?
I think I've gotta pee.
おしっこしたいんだけど
Hold it in.
（本田）我慢してください
（木下）えっ？
I'm joking.
冗談です
Use that.
（本田）そこに…
（木下）えっ？
（本田）冗談です
I'm joking.
You're not gonna tell the PM about Endou-san?
遠藤さんのこと
デスクに上げないんですか？
He's got his hands full with the director.
監督につきっきりだろ？
I don't want to give him more things to worry about.
それに これ以上
本田さんに負担かけたくないよ
He can't take much more stress.
あの人 気が小さいからさ
（あおい）でも…
（矢野）やっぱ何かあった？
But—
Something happened, huh?
It's just... Miyamori was asking me for some advice.
（太郎）
ああ ちょっと宮森(みやもり)が俺に
相談したいことがあるたいで
It's not about work. You know, personal stuff.
あっ 仕事の話じゃなくて
プライベートの
I'm always ready to drop some sage advice.
俺って相談しやすい
タイプらしくって…
What are you talking about?!
何言ってるんですか！
Right... We can't really discuss it in front of everyone.
そっか～ ここじゃ
話しづらいよな
You're so much trouble...
（太郎）世話が焼けるな～
（あおい）ああ…
I get that you don't want to tell Honda-san, but at least let Yano-san know!
（あおい）
本田さんに話せないなら
矢野さんに相談したほうが
いいんじゃないですか？
But she's scary.
矢野さん怖いんだもん
宮森 怖くないもん
You... not so much.
はあ～ 戻ります
We're done here.
I didn't mean it like that!
いやいや そうじゃなくて
宮森 優しいからさ～！
I meant that you're so nice and understanding!
You'll help me, won't you?
聞いてくれるよね？
ほら 座って座って
Just take a seat.
Everyone else is so childish. I've had it up to here.
いやもう みんな大人げなくて
イヤになっちゃうよ
I don't care how childish you think they are.
高梨さんの愚痴じゃなくて
Why is Endou-san quitting?
どうして降りるって
言ってるんですか？　遠藤さん
It's because of the last cut in episode 8.
いや ８話のラストカットの件でさ
He and Shimoyanagi-san got a bit upset.
下柳(しもやなぎ)さんと
なんかちょっともめて…
Huh? The CG director?
（あおい）
えっ なんで３Ｄ監督と？
It all started here. Yes, at Musani.
それはな まさにこの
ムサニで事件は始まった
We made some explosion demos too.
（若手スタッフ）
ダミーで爆発も作ってみたんです
作画さんの参考になれば
The animators could use these as reference.
I like it.
（木下）
いいね～
We already asked Endou-san to draw this stuff, though.
ああ でもこの爆発
遠藤さんに作画発注してますけど
But this has real impact!
いやこれ 迫力あるよ～！
Madoka Hironori
Episode Director
I didn't know CG could look this great.
（円(まどか)）
３Ｄでここまで出来るんすね～
Thank you.
（若手スタッフ）
ありがとうございます
So what's your call?
We can take care of it, if you want.
（下柳）
どうします？　やろうと思えば
こっちでもできますけど
Shimoyanagi Yuuichirou
3D Director
If Endou-kun hasn't started yet,
could you let him know not to?
遠藤君が まだ手つけてなかったら
止めてくれる？
Let's go with these CG explosions.
爆発も３Ｄでいこう
Huh?
（遠藤）
えっ なんで？
But why?
The CG team made explosions too.
３Ｄ班が爆発も作ってくれて
But those were supposed to be hand-drawn.
そこは作画でやるはずだったろ？
The director watched the CG version and decided to go with that.
でも ３Ｄが作ったやつ見て
監督 これでいくって
He said it'd be way cooler.
作画なんかより カッコいいって
You haven't started yet anyway, right?
だって遠藤さん
まだ手つけてないっすよね？
I was just about to!
これからやろうと思ってたんだよ！
See, you haven't even done it yet.
やっぱり まだじゃないですか
Since the cut's my time to shine,
I was going to nail it!
見せ場なんだから
じっくりやろうと思ったんだよ！
Let me do it instead!
３Ｄじゃなくて俺に描かせろ！
作画でけれんみ出すところだろ？
It needs some of that hand-drawn flair!
Then I'll ask the director.
じゃあ 監督に聞いてみます
（木下）
う～ん 俺 今 立て込んでるから
Sorry, I'm too busy.
Ask Shimoyanagi-kun directly.
下柳君に直接相談してみて
はい
Okay.
Endou-san wants to draw it himself.
遠藤さん
自分が描くって言ってます
He said CG isn't flashy enough.
３Ｄだと けれんみが
出せないって
Is he already done?
遠藤さん 上がったの？
Not yet.
（太郎）
いえ まだこれからっす
He's also the AD for the episode, right?
遠藤さん この話数の
作監もやってるんでしょ？
Since AD work is more important,
doing keyframes can't be his top priority.
どうしても作監作業が
優先になるから
自分の原画 後回しに
なっちゃうんじゃない？
Wouldn't it be good to lighten his workload?
少しでも負担を軽くして
あげたほうがよくないかな？
What did the director say?
（遠藤）
監督 なんて言ってた？
He said Shimoyanagi-san should decide.
下柳さんが決めていいって
Huh?
Shimoyanagi-san said he doesn't want to wait for your keyframes, so he'll take care of it.
下柳さん 遠藤さんの
作画待つのやだから
３Ｄでやるって言ってました
はっ… 早さだけの
問題じゃないだろ？
It's not an issue of speed!
But now we don't need you to—
ですが作画は不要になったんで…
You don't need me?!
“不要”ってなんだよ！
So you don't need animators if you can use CG?!
３Ｄさえあれば
作画はいらないのかよ！
What are you getting so worked up about?
なんでそんなに怒ってんですか？
Isn't less to worry about a good thing?
楽できていいじゃないですか
2D anime is about hand-drawn animation! Not 3D!
２Ｄアニメの
一番の見せ場は作画だろ！
３Ｄじゃねえ！
Tell him that!
そう伝えとけ！
Huh? Endou-san!
えっ ちょっ… 遠藤さん！
He said he can't trust the show to CG.
（太郎）
３Ｄに見せ場は任せられないって
That CG is just the frosting on the cake.
３Ｄは２Ｄの
おまけだって言ってました
おっ… おまけ？
Frosting?
Endou-san must hate CG.
遠藤さん ３Ｄを
全否定してるんすかね？
Hate CG?
全否定って…
Modern CG can do everything hand-drawn animation can, given enough time.
今の３Ｄは時間さえあれば
作画でできることは
ほぼ表現できるんだよ
It was the director's decision. I'm doing it.
監督が決めたんだから
作業を進めるよ
Mukai-kun, keep going as you were.
（下柳）向井(むかい)君 そのまま進めて
（太郎）う～ん…
Understood.
（向井）はい
（太郎）おっ！
Then find a wonderful girlfriend who doesn't drink and have her help you!
（あおい）
じゃあ 酔っ払わない
ステキな彼女を見つけて
助けてもらってくださ～い
Wait!
ああ 待って 待って！
マジピンチだから助けて！
I'm actually in over my head here! Don't hang—
切らないで！
Well, I'm sure they'll have calmed down by tomorrow morning.
まあ あしたになれば
２人共 冷静になってるっしょ
Good morning!
おはようございま～す
Huh? What are you drawing?
あれっ 何描いてんですか？
The last cut.
（遠藤）
例のラストカットだよ
But I told you it'll be done in CG.
だから３Ｄでいくって
言ってるのに…
Huh? I thought we agreed it was to be hand-drawn!
えっ？　作画って話で
落ち着いたんじゃないのかよ？
That's weird. What made you think that?
いや おっかしいな～
どこで そんな話に
なっちゃったんだろう？
That's what I'd like to know!
こっちが聞きてえよ！
Which would you go with?
お前は
どっちがいいと思ってんだ？
I'm a fan of hand-drawn animation...
おっ… 俺的には
作画 好きなんすけどね
But you see, it's the age of CG now.
でもほら 時代は
３Ｄじゃないんすか？
Hand-drawn effects are pretty old hat now.
エフェクト作画の時代は
終わったんすよ
Endou-san?!
遠藤さん？
So pretty much, it boils down to this being your fault.
どう考えても高梨さんに
問題があると思います
Really? I tried to mediate as best I could.
そうか？
ネゴシエーターとして
やるだけのことはやったんだけど
If you'd just helped me on the phone...
だからあの時 宮森が
電話に出てくれてれば
I was out drinking.
私 お酒飲んでましたし
That's why I said I don't like women who drink.
だから俺 酒飲む女はＮＧ
じゃあ私 ＮＧ女なんで
失礼しま～す
Well, then excuse me. I'm leaving.
Wait!
あっ ちょっとちょっと！
Sort it out yourself.
自分でなんとかしてください
I'm telling Honda-san.
本田さんには
私が報告しておきます
No! Anything but that!
（太郎）
やめて～！　それだけはやめて！
You can't tell him about this now!
本田さんに
言える状況じゃないだろ？
And you know, we PMs should be stuck together!
それにさ 制作同士は
以心伝心じゃん？
You mean stick together!
（あおい）
それを言うなら一心同体です！
That's it! I know you love this kind of drama!
それそれ！
お前こういうトラブル好きだろ？
That kind of talk is why everyone gets mad at you in the first place!
（あおい）
だからそういう余計なひと言で
みんなを怒らせてるんじゃ
ないんですか？
That's not true! Hold on!
そんなことないよ
ちょっと待ってよ！
Miyamori, did you lose weight?
あっ 宮森　最近痩せた？
No. In fact, gained a little.
むしろちょっと太りました
I know! You got a haircut!
髪切ったでしょ？
Yeah, two months ago.
２か月 切ってません
Wow, that's a great new outfit! Looks fantastic on you!
あっ… その服 初めてみるけどさ
似合うね～！
I wear these clothes all the time.
これ 前から着てるんですけど
Uh...
（太郎）えっと…
（宮森）もういいです
Just give up.
What if Endou-san quits the entire Exodus project?
遠藤さん「えくそだすっ！」
全体から降りることになったら
どうすんだよ？
We'll all be screwed!
ムサニ 大ピンチだろ？
Just help me convince him!
とにかく一緒に説得してくれよ！
You don't have to walk me to the restroom.
トイレまで
ついて来なくてもいいでしょ
I'm not a criminal.
俺 犯罪者みたいじゃん
You are, in a way.
ある意味 罪人(つみびと)ですからね
I'm not gonna run away.
（木下）
逃げたりしないって
Just get it over with.
いいから早く済ませてください
Don't listen to me go!
（木下）
音 聞かないでよね
I'm not, trust me!
聞きませんよ！
The storyboards are a bit raw,
but this chicken sure ain't!
コンテは上がらないけど
から揚げは
揚がっちゃったね
Good one, huh?
なんちゃって
（遠藤）おっ！
（遠藤の妻）あら おかえり
Oh, welcome home!
I'm back.
ただいま
What happened? Did you forget something?
どうしたの？　忘れ物？
I got an early start today and made really good progress,
ああ いや…
いつもより
ちょっと早く入ったからな
思ったよりペース上がって
今日の分 終わっちゃったよ
so I'm already finished for the day.
My meetings got canceled too.
その後の打ち合わせは
キャンセルになったし
Is that so?
そうなんだ
Weren't you supposed to be
working at the cleaners now?
まだクリーニング店
行かなくていいのか？
Someone asked to swap shifts,
so I'm doing the late shift today.
遅番の人に
変わってくれって言われて
もう少ししたら出る
I'll be leaving in a bit.
I see.
そっか
Would you like me to make some coffee?
コーヒーでもいれよっか？
（遠藤）
いや ダリーズでも行くか？
Why don't we go to Dully's instead?
No, let's do coffee ourselves.
We ought to be saving, anyway.
え～ うちで飲もうよ
節約しないと
ローンもあるんだし
Remember our mortgage.
I'm telling you, locking me up won't get this done any faster.
だからさ
こんなことしても上がらないものは
上がらないんだけれど
You trying to sabotage this whole thing? Again?
作画崩壊させる気ですか？　また
A text? Who's it from?
誰？　誰からのメール？
Your carrier. You get a discount if you upgrade your phone now.
あっ 電話会社から
機種変キャンペーンのお知らせです
おほほ～ ほへ～
The Full-Naked Hypnotist?
（本田）
「ハダカの催眠術師」ですか？
It was really popular, wasn't it?
（本田）
すごい人気でしたもんね
It's been eleven years since then.
もう11年前だけどね
I was so young...
あのころは若かったな
This year's prize for best director goes to Kinoshita Seiichi.
（司会）
今年度の個人賞を受賞された―
木下誠一(せいいち)監督です
His first work,
初監督作品
「ハダカの催眠術師」が大ヒット
The Full-Naked Hypnotist, was a huge hit.
一昨年放映された
「ハニーとクローバー」は
Nectar & Clover, which aired two years ago,
was popular not only with anime fans,
but the wider TV audience too.
アニメファンのみならず
幅広い層に好評を得ました
Then this year, his Grief in the Shell
garnered rave reviews.
そして本年度「望遠機動隊」は
海外でも高く評価されました
それでは木下監督
ひと言お願いします
Kinoshita-san, a few words, if you will!
え～ 個人賞ありがとうございます
Thank you for this award.
However, I don't care about works past,
ですが 僕は
過去の作品には興味ありません
as I am always looking towards the future!
なぜなら
いつも未来を見てるからです
Please look forward to my first
original work, Boing-Boing Paradise!
次の初オリジナル作品
「ぷるんぷるん天国」に
期待してください！
Boing-Boing Paradise
Disruptive Dimensions
The animation's boingtastic (rofl)
I hope you get it now.
It's just too erotic! The PTA is so mad!!!
Three recap eps... Where is Director Kinoshita?
The epic fail of the season, BoingPara gave birth to words like "boingity"
and had a recap episode of recap episodes. If that wasn't
enough now it seems that the director is MIA
[Trolls] Official site raided and shut down
BoingPara now has nowhere to run. The flames fanned by the show have finally
reached the official site. The comment box has been overrun by trolls, who abused
a bug to post ASCII art and inappropriate content, which was unmoderated and posted
public instantly. Removing the comment box just made the situation worse, triggering
a DDoS attack
Official event backfires as the creators apologize... No surprises.
Kinoshita Seiichi is done for!
I for one liked Boing-Boing Paradise.
（本田）
でも「ぷるんぷるん天国」
僕は面白かったです
The characters were well-rounded, and the jokes were pretty good.
キャラも立ってましたし
ギャグのキレもよかったです
It was supposed to be moe, not comedy.
萌(も)えを目指したんだよ
ギャグじゃない
I know you're excited to be directing again.
（本田）
久しぶりの監督作で
力が入ってるのは分かります
You've been laying low for six years, after all.
６年 干されてんですもんね
干されてないよ！
ＯＶＡの監督はやったし
I wasn't laying low! I did OVAs,
not to mention some web series!
ＷＥＢアニメだって…
If we fall any further behind,
this is doomed to end up like Boing-Boing.
（本田）
とにかく これ以上遅れると
「ぷる天」の二の舞です
No!
イヤだ！
The animation is quite solid so far.
（本田）
作画もここまで安定してます
最後まで頑張りましょう
Let's see this through to the end.
（ノック）
（丸川）から揚げ持ってきたよ
I brought some fried chicken.
Get it while it's fresh and crispy!
（丸川）
サクサク揚げたてだよ
Careful, it's hot.
熱いから気をつけてね
Keep it up!
じゃあ 頑張ってね
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
絵コンテ１枚上げたら
１個あげます
You can have one for each storyboard page you finish.
ガー 冷めちゃうよ～！
They're gonna get cold!
Uomachi
（北野(きたの)）
珍しいよな
遠藤から呼び出すなんて
It's rare for you to invite me out like this, Endou.
Well, it's been a while.
（遠藤）
いや ちょっとご無沙汰だったんで
He works with me at Musani.
ああ こいつは今
ムサニで一緒にやってて
He wanted to meet you, Kitano-san.
北野さんに
会ってみたいっていうんで
When I was little, I loved your Superspace Jelly Lacross!
堀田(ほった)です　俺 子供の頃
Hotta Hikaru
Keyframe Animator
北野さんがやってた
「超飛空羊羹(ようかん)マジダス」
見てました！
（少年）
うりゃ～！
The Kitano Circus was so cool!
（堀田）
北野サーカス
超カッコよかったっす！
Kitano Saburou
Animator
That's what inspired me to work in this industry!
それで俺 業界入りました！
アハッ！　きみ まだ
生まれてなかったろ？
You weren't even born when that aired.
（堀田）
再放送で見ました
I watched the reruns!
I even got the blu-ray box set!
ブルーレイボックスも
買いましたから
He's drawing a scene where the characters ride a bike across a minefield.
こいつ今 主人公が
バイクで地雷原走るとこ描いてて
いや～ 難しいっすよ
It's so hard.
How do you make explosions look so cool?
爆発とか どうやったら
カッコよくなりますかね？
Ah, you know...
う～ん それは…
（携帯電話の着信音）
Incoming Call
Takanashi Tarou
Go ahead. Take the call.
（北野）
いいよ　出ろよ
It's fine.
いや 大丈夫です
Takanashi Tarou
Incoming Call
えっ ウソ～
No way!
（堀田）例の件ですかね？
（遠藤）だろうな
Is it still about that thing?
I guess so.
今更なんだっつうの！
I'm surprised they bothered calling!
（北野）
何かあったのか？
Did something happen?
It's no big deal.
いや ちょっと…
遠藤さんが描くはずだったカット
３Ｄでいくことになって
The cut Endou-san was working on ended up being done in CG.
おい 余計なこと言うなよ！
Hey, know when to keep your mouth shut.
Isn't that mean?
あんまりですよね
３Ｄなんか時間ばっかかかって
3D animation is a waste of time.
There's no real flavor or nice feel to it.
しかも出来たもんに
味も情緒もないし
Right?
だよな～
Not to mention it lacks the joy and fun of actually drawing things.
それに３Ｄには
絵を描く喜びとか
楽しさがないっすよ
Yeah! Move to Hollywood if you want to do CG that much!
（遠藤）
そうそう！
そんなに３Ｄアニメが好きなら
カリフォルニアにでも
行けっつうんだ！
Right, Kitano-san?
ですよね？　北野さん
I'm teaching 3D animators about the tricks of Japanimation.
（北野）
俺 今 ３Ｄにジャパニメーションの
コツを教えてるよ
Japanimation?
ジャパニメーションって
なんのコツっすか？
What tricks?
３Ｄソフトを使って
絵と時間のデフォルメをな
Image processing techniques and effects like slow-mo with 3D software.
彼らは絵は描けなくても
アニメが好きだからな
They can't draw, but they like anime.
They learn quickly too. They're a joy to teach.
覚えるのも早いし
教えてても気持ちがいいんだ
Are you serious?
マジっすか
Kitano-san, why waste your time with that?
北野さん
なんでそんなことやるんですか？
俺たち絵描きが歩み寄って
We were raised on hand-drawing techniques.
３Ｄアニメーターの使う
ツールの長所も短所も知って
We know the strengths and weaknesses of the 3D animators' tools.
Shouldn't we work together to make the final product the best it can be?
彼らと協力して アニメの質を
上げていくんじゃないのか？
I didn't know you were on their side.
北野さん
そっちの人間だったんすか？
Blindly rejecting CG won't benefit anyone.
（北野）
いじけて３Ｄを否定しても
何もよくならんぞ
But those CG guys are stealing our jobs left and right!
でも現にこうやって
３Ｄのヤツらに仕事取られて…
If you plan on blaming others when things don't go well, you might as well quit!
うまくいかないことを
人のせいにしているようなヤツは
辞めちまえよ！
（遠藤）
あっ… じゃあもう俺たちみたいな
手描きのアニメーターは
So are you saying those who animate by hand like us aren't needed anymore?
必要ないっていうんですか？
お前の描く絵が
通用しなくなっても
Even if the old techniques go by the wayside,
your skills are still needed.
技術を生かす方法は
あるんじゃないのか？
Not anybody can draw something special,
be it on a tablet or paper.
鉛筆がタブレットに変わっても
センスは必要とされる
Why don't you give it a try?
まあ お前も
勉強してみればどうだ？
No way!
（堀田）
いや 俺は生涯
一手描きアニメーターっす！
I'll do hand-drawn animation for life!
アハハ…
Ah, Shimoyanagi-san!
（太郎）
あっ 下柳さん
Good evening!
（太郎･あおい）
お疲れさまでした！
Good evening.
お疲れ
Evening.
Takanashi-kun, what happened to that explosion scene in the end?
高梨君さあ 結局
爆発のシーンはどうなったの？
Did Endou-san agree to doing it with CG?
遠藤さん ３Ｄでいくっていうの
了承してくれた？
（太郎）いや 作監 降りました
（あおい）えっ？
Well, he quit being AD.
Huh? Why?
えっ なんで？
I don't know either.
（太郎）
いや 俺にも分からないっす
I didn't know it'd turned into such a mess.
そんな 大ごとになってるとは
思わなかったよ
Will we be all right?
大丈夫なの？
Totally! I'm gonna fix all this up!
全然大丈夫です
俺がなんとかしますから！
Yeah, please do.
（下柳）
いや ホントなんとかしてよ
じゃあ
Later.
任せてくださ～い！
Leave it to me!
まあ お前はもういいよ
俺に任せておけ
It's okay. You can go now.
Leave it to me.
Yasuhara Ema
Keyframe Animator
（あおい）
絵麻(えま)！
Ema!
（絵麻）
あっ おいちゃん
Oi-chan!
Just get off work?
（あおい）今 帰り？
（絵麻）うん
Yeah.
What are you making?
Rich in nutrients (Vitamin C)
Healthy
Eggs
（あおい）何 作るの？
（絵麻）オムライス
Rice omelet. Want to come over?
（絵麻）
おいちゃんも うちで食べる？
Yeah, of course! I'll bring salad and jelly!
えっ いいの？
じゃあ私 サラダとプリン買うね！
It's Alpine!
（あおい）
あるぴんだ！　さすがプロ！
That's a pro for you!
I almost don't want to dig into it!
食べるのもったいな～い
Let's just eat.
いいから食べよ
いただきま～す！
All right!
Did Endou-san really quit being AD for episode 8?
（絵麻）
遠藤さん
８話の作監 降りるってホント？
I heard Iguchi-san and
Ogasawara-san talking about it.
（絵麻）
井口(いぐち)さんと小笠原(おがさわら)さんが
話してるの聞いちゃって
遠藤さんのカット ３Ｄ班で
やることになったんだって？
So the CG team ended up doing Endou-san's cut?
Apparently.
（あおい）
みたい
I only heard about it from Takanashi-san myself.
私も高梨さんから
聞いただけだから
More and more is being done with CG.
だんだん３Ｄの仕事
増えてってるもんね
私も ちょっと不安
I'm a bit worried too.
この先 アニメって
どうなっていくのかな？
What's anime going to be like in the future?
（あおい）
う～ん　みーちゃんも
進路決める時 迷ってたもんね
Mii-chan also thought about it a lot when she picked her job.
She said that CG is probably the future, so she decided to go that route.
みーちゃんは結局
３ＤＣＧのほうが
将来有望かもって
そっちに進んだけど
う～ん　将来か
The future, huh?
（太郎）
はい ８話です
Yes, episode 8.
I was wondering if you could fill in as the AD.
ぜひ作監のピンチヒッターを
お願いできないかと思いまして
Like pinch hit for us.
そう 代打です
ここは俺を…
Could you help m—
I mean, Musani and—
いや ムサニを助けると思って！
お願いします！
あっ なんだよ！
いきなり切ることないじゃん！
What the hell? Don't hang up on a guy like that!
うわっ！　なんだ宮森か
Oh, it's just you, Miyamori.
“なんだ”じゃないですよ
What do you mean by that?
Man, what a disaster...
（太郎）
ああもう 朝からクタクタだよ
Are you looking for an AD to replace Endou-san?
もしかして 遠藤さんの
代わりの作監 捜してるんですか？
Finding someone else is faster than trying to convince him.
遠藤さん説得するより
他の作監 捜したほうが早いだろ？
Are you giving up?
諦めちゃうんですか？
あの人 へそ曲げると
頑固なんだよな
He's stubborn when he gets upset.
本田さんに
絶対相談するべきですよ！
You should totally talk with Honda-san!
いや これは俺の戦いだ
No. This is my fight.
I'll talk with Honda-san once I've come up with my next move.
本田さんには
次の手を決めてから報告する
That's what it means to take responsibility!
それが責任ってもんだろ？
Come on, that line was totally cool.
えっ 今 俺ちょっと
カッコいいこと言ったのに
Storage
Honda-kun...
（木下）本田君
（本田）なんですか？
Yes?
（木下）眠いんだけど
（本田）僕もです
I'm sleepy.
So am I.
Honda-kun...
（木下）本田君
（本田）はい
Yes?
My back's aching.
（木下）
腰痛い
We could do radio exercises together.
一緒にラジオ体操でも
しましょうか
Aren't we like Ibuse Masuji's salamanders?
なんかさ 俺たちって
「山椒魚(さんしょううお)」みたいだよね？
We got too fat, and now we can't get out of the cave.
井伏(いぶせ)鱒二(ますじ)の
プクプク太って岩屋から
出られなくなってさ
知ってる？
Do you know the story?
知ってますけど その話
転がしたくありません
I do, but I don't want to talk about it.
I just can't think clearly right now.
なんか考えが
まとまんないんだよね
Do you want a recap episode to give you more time?
もう総集編入れて
楽になりたいですか？
No!
イヤだ！
A recap for the last episode?
I've never heard of such a thing!
前代未聞ですよ
最終回が総集編
I don't want Exodus to end like that.
僕は「えくそだすっ！」を
そんなふうに終わらせたくないです
Neither do I!
俺だってやだよ もう
Then keep at it!
（本田）
だったら頑張りましょう！
I'll be on my way then.
（あおい）
じゃあ失礼します
Ah, Miyamori-san!
（瀬川(せがわ)）あっ 宮森さん
（あおい）うん？
What happened with Endou-kun?
（瀬川）遠藤君 どうなった？
（あおい）えっ？
Where did you—
（あおい）なんで？
（瀬川）蛇の道はヘビってね
I have my sources.
He hasn't returned to the studio yet.
まだ会社に出てきてないです
I see...
Segawa Misato
Animation Director
そう…
His special touch on those effects got him noticed in the first place, so he must've taken it hard.
まあ彼は最初
エフェクトの作画で認められたから
ショックだったんでしょう
He still has to support himself and his family for thirty more years. I do as well.
遠藤君も私も
あと30年は描いて
食べてかなきゃいけないのにね
それはそうと
９話の作業に影響出ないわよね？
That aside, there won't be any
new effects in episode 9, right?
The last cut in 8 and the first in 9 are connected.
８話のラストと９話の頭
つながってるでしょ？
Don't they need to match each other?
爆発の処理を
合わせる必要があるんじゃない？
I'll make sure there won't be any problems.
影響出ないようにします！
Miyamori!
（遠藤）宮森
（あおい）あっ？
遠藤さん！
Endou-san?
There's something I'd like to ask you.
ちょっと頼みたいことが
あるんだけど
あっ ちょっと失礼します
Excuse me for a moment.
Miyamori speaking.
あっ はい宮森です
It's Hotta.
（堀田）
あっ 堀田です
９話の冒頭の爆発シーン
I finished all five explosions cuts in the beginning of episode 9.
５カット 全部上げました
Huh?
（あおい）えっ？
（堀田）９話が作画だったら
If 9's hand-drawn, then episode 8 has to use Endou-san's keyframes, right?
遠藤さんの８話も作画っすよね？
同じシーンなら
作画で統一しなきゃマズいっしょ
It's the same scene, so they have to match!
Exodus!
Hotta
Animator
3D Reference
You don't want to replace his keyframes with CG, right?
遠藤さんの原画
３Ｄにするなんて言わないよね？
（あおい）あっ それは…
（堀田）とにかく
I—
Anyway, I'm done.
俺はもう上げたんで
回収に来てください
You can pick them up.
あの 堀田さん？　え～！
Uh, Hotta-san...
Eh?!
Huh? Miyamori?
（太郎）
ああ 宮森
大声出して どうかしたのか？
What's with all the ruckus?
Takanashi-san! This is all your fault!
（あおい）高梨さんのせいですよ！
（太郎）えっ？
Hotta-san hand-drew the explosions in episode 9!
９話の爆発シーン 堀田さんが
作画で上げちゃったって！
I see... So now we're in this together!
よし　これで俺と
同じ土俵に上がったな
Hello?
Ah, long time no see.
Of course. I'm not going to lose this time.
Next time on Shirobako:
"Idepon Miyamori: Be Invoked"
Idepon Miyamori:
Be Invoked
（渡辺）
はい　ああ ご無沙汰してます
いいですよ
次は負けませんから
次回
「ＳＨＩＲＯＢＡＫＯ(シロバコ)」